<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Geoffrey van Wyk</title><link href="https://geoffreyvanwyk.dev/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="https://geoffreyvanwyk.dev/feeds/all.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>https://geoffreyvanwyk.dev/</id><updated>2023-10-28T00:00:00+02:00</updated><subtitle>Computer Programmer</subtitle><entry><title>How I got started</title><link href="https://geoffreyvanwyk.dev/how-i-got-started.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2023-10-28T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2023-10-28T00:00:00+02:00</updated><author><name>Geoffrey Bernardo van Wyk</name></author><id>tag:geoffreyvanwyk.dev,2023-10-28:/how-i-got-started.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;From chemical engineering to computer programming&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;My first introduction to computer programming was in the form of &lt;a href="https://fortran-lang.org/"&gt;Fortran&lt;/a&gt; in
a first-year second-semester module at the University of Stellenbosh in the
1990s. Computer programming was only one half of the module; the other half was
dedicated to &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mass_balance"&gt;mass balances&lt;/a&gt; in chemical engineering. During class I could
not follow the lecturer, partly because he was not speaking loudly or clearly
enough and partly because this was a completely new concept for me. If I missed
something he said earlier in the lecture, what he said later was a mystery.
There was no prescribed book, and the booklet that accompanied the course was
not helpful at all. Eventually I realized there must be a book about Fortran in
the library of the engineering faculty. I found one! From that point onwards the
course was smooth sailing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Years later I was working as a chemical engineering technician. One day while
driving home after work one of my friends showed me a copy of an article that
described how the next largest prime number had been calculated recently. Out of
interest I wanted to find a way to do the calculations myself. The only tool I
had was Microsoft Excel spreadsheets and it seemed to me that it was perfectly
capable of performing the task. With my first attempt, I would enter a formula
in the top cell of a column then use the fill tool to drag the calculation down
the column until I found a prime number; then repeat the step in the next column
to find the next prime number, and so forth. Yet I knew there must be an
automatic way. I looked through the Excel help files without success, and
eventually came upon a part of Excel with a big white editor that would
highlight some letters that I would type in it. But I had no idea what it was
for. I set out to the company library and found a book on
&lt;a href="https://learn.microsoft.com/en-us/office/vba/api/overview/"&gt;Visual Basic for Applications&lt;/a&gt; and so started my second foray into computer
programming. The big white editor was for Visual Basic. I eventually wrote a
little function that would populate the cells on a spreadsheet with the sequence
of prime numbers in dramatic fashion. My next program with VBA was for creating
an Excel spreadsheet formula for calculating the molecular mass of a molecule.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of my colleagues later gave me a complete video course on &lt;em&gt;Visual Basic 6&lt;/em&gt;
in &lt;abbr title="Compact Disc"&gt;CD&lt;/abbr&gt; format which I enjoyed tremendously. With &lt;abbr title="Visual Basic 6"&gt;VB6&lt;/abbr&gt; I built a unit conversion
app, but never completed it. Later, with &lt;a href="https://learn.microsoft.com/en-us/dotnet/visual-basic/"&gt;Visual Basic .Net&lt;/a&gt;, I built
&lt;a href="https://sourceforge.net/projects/timepiece/"&gt;Timepiece&lt;/a&gt;, an alarm clock, stopwatch and countdown timer for your Windows
desktop, which I am proud of. I published it on SourceForge and it has been
downloaded more than 5000 times. I once saw that somebody made a video review of
it, but I cannot find it anymore.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The blogs of &lt;a href="https://joelonsoftware.com/"&gt;Joel Spolsky&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="https://blog.codinghorror.com/"&gt;Jeff Atwood&lt;/a&gt; cemented my interest in
computer science. Jeff Atwood's account of how he first worked on StackOverflow
alone, but then marshalled his previous colleagues to join him, inspired me to
think about switching careers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Seeking to learn more about computer science, I read the book &lt;em&gt;Think like a
Computer Scientist&lt;/em&gt;. It also taught me the &lt;a href="https://python.org/"&gt;Python&lt;/a&gt; programming language.
Later editions of the book were retitled to &lt;a href="https://www.amazon.com/Think-Python-Like-Computer-Scientist/dp/1491939362/ref=sr_1_1?crid=1DSQY95MZ95AP&amp;amp;keywords=think+python+3rd+edition&amp;amp;qid=1698147094&amp;amp;sprefix=think+python+%252Caps%252C348&amp;amp;sr=8-1&amp;amp;_encoding=UTF8&amp;amp;tag=geoffreyvanwy-20&amp;amp;linkCode=ur2&amp;amp;linkId=ead7d652290feaa0567a068e957cbb0a&amp;amp;camp=1789&amp;amp;creative=9325"&gt;Think Python&lt;/a&gt;. Learning that
YouTube ran on Python, I wanted to use Python to build an eminently useful
website like StackOverflow.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, I was sidetracked into learning PHP when a Christian brother who built
&lt;a href="https://wordofthehour.net/"&gt;Word of the Hour&lt;/a&gt; asked me to write a script for importing articles. PHP
became my main focus and I decided that it was time to make computer programming
my full time career.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After a failed attempt at starting an online business for advertising cars, I
eventually landed my first job as a software developer at an online fashion
store called &lt;em&gt;Spree&lt;/em&gt; which is now &lt;a href="https://superbalist.com/"&gt;Superbalist&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="stories"></category><category term="computer programming"></category><category term="getting started"></category><category term="fortran"></category><category term="php"></category><category term="python"></category><category term="moodle"></category><category term="visual basic for applications"></category><category term="chemical engineering"></category></entry></feed>